All righty, welcome back everyone.
if you're just joining us, welcome
to WordPress Accessibility Day
my name is Allie Nimmons
and I'm your host for this session.
We are about to get started
with Unmeasurable Accessibility,
The Case for Inclusive Design,
with Darice de Cuba.
Please make sure to add your
questions to the YouTube chat feed
and we will answer those together
at the end of the presentation.
Just a little bit about
Darice before we begin.
Darice is a Web Developer and Blog
Writer for the Independent News Magazine
and Website of Rotterdam
University of Applied Sciences,
where she enjoys writing a
blog, brainstorming with the team
about the editorial,
working on new designs,
optimizing pages and maintaining
and improving the WordPress website.
Being late deaf, which gives her
unique insight into inclusive design,
she likes to write down
her musings on her website.
She loves to explore the food scene in her
hometown The Hague and in the Netherlands.
She is keeping track of cool
places she finds in her food guide.
Today she's going to be explaining
Unmeasurable Accessibility,
The Case for Inclusive Design.
So I'll go ahead and
pass things over to Darice.
Okay, hi everyone!
It's exciting to be speaking
to a worldwide audience today
and I ask you to bear with me,
because I have a several screen
including my own transcriber.
So thanks to Allie for the introduction.
So you know my name is Darice
and I recap very short,
I'm a web developer so I have
experience with HTML, CSS, PHP, Sass
and of course WordPress.
And the rest you've
already been told by Allie.
And today I talk to you
about Inclusive Design
and user usability
and my own experience.
So what most people
understand under accessibility
is stuff like ARIA for screen readers,
keyboard tabbable,
colors with a minimum
contrast ratio of 4.5 to 1
and CSS @media
(prefers-reduced-motion: reduce),
that is to reduce the motion
for people who get sick from it.
And the most important thing
about all these things,
are that they are all testable
with tools or manually.
So you can have a totally
accessible website by those standards,
but yeah your website may be
very inaccessible to many people.
There are several types of disabilities.
You have visible and
non-visible disabilities
Non-visible disabilities is a
deaf or hard of hearing person,
a person with autism,
a person with brain damage,
chronic illness and depression.
And also under the
numerous chronic illnesses,
there are several kinds of disabilities.
Just to pick a few, someone with,
say, MS that makes their hands shake
which on the other hand makes it very
difficult to use a smartphone or keyboard.
So you know non-visible disability,
the person may look healthy to you,
but they may have many disabilities.
In our lifetime most of us will
have to deal with either long-term
or short-term illness,
broken bones, high stress
for long periods of times.
All kinds of illness or injuries that
can make you temporarily disabled
or disabled for
the rest of your life.
So most people aren't born disabled,
but become disabled later in life.
I became disabled later in life.
When I was 25 years old,
I had a brain hemorrhage.
And when I had that brain hemorrhage,
it disabled my left arm,
so I had to re-learn
how to use my left arm.
And for the first time at the
very young age of 25 years,
I experienced how hard
it is to use a keyboard
when you're just recovering
from a brain hemorrhage.
A year later when I was 26 years old,
I used to be hard of hearing, but
then I lost the rest of my hearing.
So one day I was still hard of hearing
and the next day I woke
up completely deaf.
So I had to like drastically
adjust my life in one day.
So I don't consider myself disabled,
rather I am made disabled by the
obstacles created by society.
A society built only for the
seeing, hearing, talking, walking,
healthy, straight, cis male, white people.
Every time I leave my home, this is what
my life looks like outside when I'm deaf.
I'm constantly
avoiding things and adjusting.
So now a few quick facts about deafness
that many people are not aware of.
There are two kinds of deafness.
You have deaf with capital D
which means a person who
culturally identifies as a deaf person.
That those persons are born deaf
or became deaf very early
in their life, as kids
and their primary language
is sign language.
Then you have people with lower d deaf,
that's people like me, amongst others
and we became deaf later in life.
And like I was hard of
hearing since I was a kid,
but I had a hearing life
and later on I became deaf.
And you have people who have had
perfect hearing their whole lifetime,
but maybe they had an accident
or they took some medication
and it is known that some heavy
medication may destroy your hearing.
And, from one day to the next, people
went from perfect hearing to deafness.
And of course their spoken
language is their primary language.
So they will depend more
on captions and transcripts
instead of sign language.
Inclusive design is a design approach
that takes as many individuals,
their background, their needs,
experience and ability into account
from day one of the project.
Accessibility is a part
of inclusive design.
We want as many people as possible
to be able to use our products.
Small examples that have a big impact.
So this is a screenshot
of deliveroo.com
I'm from the Netherlands so
we have one of those ordering,
food ordering is Deliveroo.
and I have never used Deliveroo.
I don't know how well
you can see the screen,
but basically on the screen,
I have already picked my dinner,
and now I have to pay.
And on the screen there's nowhere
there is an option, a text field,
where I can fill in that I'm deaf.
And imagine something
is wrong with my order
or the restaurant needs to contact me.
There's no way that I can
let them know that I'm deaf,
so they can please send me
an email or a text message
instead of calling.
And the same goes for the delivery person,
there is no way I can put
that they should text me.
Imagine they ring the
doorbell or something is wrong
they are going to call me, because
I can't let them know I'm deaf.
So this place lost my
business and my money,
because it's not accessible to me.
And I like ordering food, so every
time something goes wrong
this is the feeling I have.
No food for me.
So one of the good things to use
for such a website are chat widgets.
And, little by little, some
places start using a chat widget,
but they are not using them optimally
to make them accessible to everyone.
A lot of them have a bot behind those.
I, as a deaf person
have no use for a bot.
So if you're going to implement a chat
widget to communicate with the client,
you should think about
real people behind it,
reasonable waiting timess
and the widget should work
with all web browsers.
In the Netherlands, we have like
a social government, social service
and they have a chat widget
specially for deaf people,
because they know we cannot call.
But the first problem is that you
have to click like three or four times
on the website
to finally arrive on that chat widget.
And the chat widget will work with Chrome
or maybe it will work with Firefox
and every time they develop
or they make upgrades
it's like a surprise with which
browser is going to work.
Just make sure it works
in all modern browsers.
Another thing that makes your
website very inaccessible
that you may not be aware of is,
is using a no-reply email.
So you have your WordPress website
and you followed all advice to
make it accessible to screen readers,
the colors are working well,
your links work well,
but then when you interact with clients,
you will send email with a no-reply
and there will be no contact info
and the only thing you'll be
providing is a phone number.
And this has happened to me several times
and then I need to contact that company,
I have no way to do it.
So if you're gonna use a no-reply email,
make sure you do have options in that email
for people who cannot call
to contact you.
Let it be an email address
that you are reachable at,
a chat widget
or just a contact form.
Another thing is when people write weblogs,
I mean a lot of us start
WordPress as a weblog
and then we expand it with
WooCommerce and everything,
but people write so difficult.
I, as a developer, many times
I'm looking for things,
how to do things in PHP, how to do
things in Python, how to do things in CSS
and I'll stumble across a web blog
and it's written so difficult.
And it's not only weblogs,
the same government website also
has to contact many people of all
socioeconomic statuses in the country.
And I don't know if you know,
but if you make a mistake
in your social things,
you may get a fine,
but when you get a letter from them or an
email from them, it's written so difficult.
I'm a college, university graduate
and even I have difficulties
reading what are they telling me
because it's difficult.
Imagine a person with no education,
who works a low-paid job
and they get a letter like that.
So no one ever said
when reading a web blog
or a website, I wish this
was written more difficult.
So leave the difficult words out
and try to write like you're
writing for kids in sixth grade.
A photo says more than a thousand words.
This screenshot is of Specsavers
and it's a Dutch website
and after selling glasses,
they also sell hearing aids.
And if you see the
photos on this home page,
they assume that only elderly
people use hearing aids.
And that is a huge, huge
assumption that is totally off base
because like I mentioned,
I became hard of hearing, oh I think
I was born, nobody knows for sure,
but when I started school they
discovered I was hard of hearing.
So I think by the time I was 12 years
was recommended that I had hearing aids.
So imagine nowadays you have a business
and you just make an assumption
of who your client base is
and you design your website based on that.
If I was 12 years today in 2020,
I would want to scrape
hearing aids with colors
and you know, I've seen some photos,
they are very very much more fun looking,
than when back then.
And imagine you have parents who have money
or willing to spend money to
get their kids great hearing aids
and they arrive on a website
that looks like this.
And its something they'll
click away, right away
because this website assumes it's
only old people who wear hearing aids
and the products will probably not be
to the liking of a 12-year-old girl.
So when you have a website and
you focus on commercial end clients,
think very hard
of who are actually your client base,
because it can cost you
money in the long run.
So captions,
Facebook made a very very deep research.
I mean, for them it's easy, because
they can track everything.
And Facebook found out that increased
view time of videos on Facebook
was for 12 percent
when they added subtitles.
And they have a huge,
millions of people to test on
because we can count
Facebook and Instagram on it.
And captions have so many advantages
it's not only for hard of
hearing and deaf people,
but watching videos in noisy
places or the silent train coupé
and imagine you're at the library
studying, and you take a break
and you want to see some video
you're going to need captions.
It's also very handy for the
search engine optimization,
because Google cannot index
sound, but Google does index text.
So if you have captions, Google will find
your website and your videos much faster.
And when spoken language
is not your primary language,
so if you are English speaking and
maybe you understand a bit of Spanish,
but it will be handy to have captions,
maybe in English or Spanish,
but as long as you can follow extra well.
And also if the speaker have an accent,
I know I have an accent,
because I speak four languages
and not one mother tongue.
So I know I sound very confusing
and I'm sure the caption will even help
hearing people follow me along.
I don't know how many of you
are familiar with the SRT subtitle file,
but for me this SRT file
is the biggest evidence
that way more people want
caption than who don't,
because the SRT files have been popular
since the internet was fast
enough to download media.
And there are websites out there,
thousands and thousands of captions
and they are hugely popular.
So like everyone needs or
want captions on their videos,
so it shouldn't be a question if you're
gonna put a video on your website, like
should I put a caption on a video, it's
gonna cost money, it's gonna cost time,
but the answer is, yes.
Because everyone, everyone wants caption
and sometimes whether they know it
or not they'll prefer captions.
So this is another huge fact,
if you're gonna caption,
never ever do this.
Do not caption ball sounds like this.
I mean it's just offensive
to deaf people, especially
and hard of hearing people.
But when Janice in Friends is laughing,
that you do caption.
And why?
Because in this context,
one of Janice's most annoying
characteristics was her annoying laugh.
And I can imagine, I'm hard of hearing,
so I saw the whole of Friends
before I became deaf,
but now Friends is on Netflix
and a whole new generation is meeting
Friends for the first time.
And I can imagine some
who never heard Friends
who would appreciate exactly
knowing why people are annoyed
when Janice laughs.
So do think why, when
you caption something,
if you are doing the correct way
and not in the offensive way.
So everyone likes pointing out to
me that YouTube has auto captioning.
Auto-captioning is not good enough.
The first thing auto-captions
suffer from bias,
because it doesn't recognize accents
and that's also a little non-inclusive.
When you have a team of the same people.
I don't know, I'm going to pick
because most tech people are white
and high socioeconomic captioning they
are going to be thinking the same,
and not everybody is going to think
"oh, there might be people
who speak with an accent."
It fails with names.
It depends on clear articulation.
If someone mumbles,
it won't caption it right,
and it also depends how slow
someone speaks.
In practice, I sometimes
recommend people do this:
as you know, like, even for a day,
although I would like
some to do it for a week,
but if you watch YouTube a lot, mute.
Mute the sound.
and watch YouTube on mute
for a whole week long,
and only you're going to have to do it
like deaf people do: depend on captions.
Add the caption, if there are captions.
Are they going to be good?
And so I dare people who are hearing,
for a week or maybe just try a
day of watching YouTube on mute
and you'll find the
horrors of auto captioning.
So, for me, the best and good examples
are Netflix and TED.
And Netflix is the best because
English is not my first language,
but my first language is Papiamento.
I don't know how many of you know that,
because I was
born and raised on Aruba,
so unfortunately I won't find
Papiamento captions anywhere in the world,
so my next go-to is English
and not Dutch like many would think,
but English.
So when I watch a movie on Netflix,
I will always choose
the English captions first.
But even so, Netflix
has many, many options
and when I'm watching a movie
from Spain, for example,
I would put—I won't dub the language,
I will let them speak Spanish,
because I can lip read some,
but I will also choose
the Spanish captions.
Because if I know those
people are speaking Spanish,
I prefer to see Spanish captions
and on the other hand if
I'm seeing an English movie,
I know they're speaking English,
I want to see English caption.
And again this is me,
that is late deaf person,
so you should not assume that all late
deaf person has the same preference.
And that's the attitude,
there is no one deaf person.
Every deaf person—late
born, late deaf, or early deaf,
they all have their individual preference
of how they like a caption
or sign language.
And Netflix also has a very good thing
and not for deaf but for blind people,
and you have audio description.
So imagine someone who is blind is
watching a horror movie, for example,
and right now the screen is silent,
but everyone who can see is looking
at a creep creeping outside the window.
And the audio caption will
let the blind person know
that there is a creeping
person creeping outside.
So, on that point, I think Netflix
was doing very well up until now
with captioning,
but there is also one thing
you have to take into account.
Yes, when I'm watching a movie,
I don't know how many of
you know One Day at a Time?
It's a movie about American Puerto Ri—
no, a Cuban American family,
so they speak English most of the time,
but the grandma,
a lot of times, speaks Spanish.
And that's one pet peeve
I have with captioning
and while the English is the
main language being spoken,
and the moment a
character speaks Spanish
they will not caption it at all.
There will be English,
no Spanish captions,
or maybe they'll just put,
“person is speaking Spanish.”
And that is also inaccessible,
so you have to pay attention
to small details like that.
And TED
that has captions in all sorts of
lang—in all main languages
and depends how old,
how long the video has been online.
They also have podcasts, and those
podcasts have also transcription.
So for me Netflix and TED are the go
to places to see videos and talks,
and all transcriptions, not only
for the deaf and hard of hearing.
And you know, I love to acquire
knowledge and follow talks,
but podcasts are a new
point of inaccessibility.
But This American Life understands this.
They had all their archives transcribed
that were years ago
and they did it in a few months.
They transcribed all their podcasts.
And since then every time
an episode is published,
within 24 hours,
it will have a transcription.
And they have done, you can, I have a link
under this slide you can look it up later
and you have other statistics,
they did a huge research and
since they have been captioning
their review—their listeners has gone up,
because Google can index,
caption—transcriptions.
So they have an increase of visitors,
they have an increase of unique visitors.
They can see that the
transcriptions are being read
and they can see they have
more people visiting their podcast.
And why transcripts matter,
there's a huge list.
Because podcasts right
now, without transcriptions,
they are inaccessible to deaf people,
hard of hearing people,
people with hearing sensitivity,
people with ADHD,
people in noisy environmentss,
people in silent environments
as the train or a library.
And transcripts are
also good for the search engine,
people's primary language isn't English,
and also for fast
referencing or quoting.
So imagine you have a
podcast and it was a hit
and you have it on your WordPress website.
Your WordPress website is super accessible.
You have a podcast that just went viral,
but now you have a problem:
you don't have transcripts.
So Google won't be indexing it.
And you're going to lose
out on a huge group of people
for which it is inaccessible.
And that fast referencing or quoting:
imagine a journalist came to your website
to write about your podcast
and the person has, really doesn't have
time to go listen to huge podcast.
And in this sense,
transcripts are very good,
because people can scan them really fast
looking for the point
and they can quote from it
and they can reference it in an article
or on another website.
So the advantages of having
transcripts are enormous.
So how inclusion works.
and why I'm going to tell you this,
because when you have a project
and maybe even if it's a small project,
it's always good to have
someone outside our bubble
giving you feedback
and their point of view on your product.
It doesn't help you to have a bubble
of the same people who think like you,
are the same culture, all of you.
So diversity is having
a seat at the table.
Inclusion is having a voice,
and belonging is
having that voice heard.
I'm a person who can be considered
a diversity in the Netherlands,
because I am not Dutch.
I'm chronically ill and I'm deaf.
and many times that happens
that people ask me to join them
and to be, you know, the other voice.
And that's very nice to be sitting
there and it's nice to be talking,
but sometimes you talk and
people don't listen.
And so it's very important
when you expand your bubble
to really be aware: am I really
listening to this person's voice.
I'm not saying you have to do
everything someone tells you,
but one should really listen
and you know comprehend
what they are being told
about their website, about the product.
And that's the best way to be inclusive.
And now I'm going to
give you a perspective,
because since I've been doing this,
I got that question many many times:
but it costs money,
it costs money, it costs money.
And the first thing you have to
think about when you have a budget
and you're getting ready
for stuff, whatever project.
So you look: I'm going to use WordPress,
that's free, thank you, that's free.
The hosting is going to cost money
and maybe I will have to hire a programmer,
but, in that budget, you should
also think about accessibility.
That should also be from day one,
because if you're going to add it later,
it's going to cost even more money.
So day one you have your budget,
accessibility is going to
be part of your budget.
And this is the perspective:
abled people will say
disabled people are only what,
like five percent increase
in our web audience?
Who cares about making the web accessible.
And also abled people: our
sign-ups increased by five percent.
Bonuses for everyone!
So that's really something
you should always think about
when you're going to start a project.
So thank you for listening and
do you have questions for me?
Wonderful, thank you so much,
that was amazing. I learned a ton.
I was tweeting through the whole thing.
I really appreciate everything
that you just shared.
I do have the questions pulled up
so I will make sure that
we go through them
from first ones to the
most recent. Let me go back.
Okay, so the first question that we have:
How many fonts should I
use when designing a website?
I found some websites
using more than two fonts.
Okay the font thing,
I think just not only for disabled people,
I think… like I like gifs
and I get annoyed if there are too many
gifs on the website I'm trying to read,
but one or two is okay.
Okay, I do actually design
long-read web pages for my job
and I stand by three fonts.
I will use one for the headers,
one for the body,
and one for the block quotes,
and maybe a fourth one, but just
for the small text, the captions,
because if I caption a photo, I will
always do that in a monotype space,
but no more than four.
You should always make sure they're
like in some flow and to just four.
I know it's very hard, I mean there
are people who are font experts
and I don't think I'm a font expert,
but like on Typekit from
Adobe and Google fonts,
you can always Google
the font combination
and they will teach you
what combinations work
So you don't have to
guess and mix and match,
but I will keep it four fonts max.
and which of two are the main ones:
one for the header and one for the body.
Next question: Do you
see enough changes in diversity
in relation to digital accessibility?
How can we improve and
what area needs it most?
What is the first thing you
address when you start a project?
So that's three questions in one.
Okay, I mostly advise people.
And then it's like,
I don't know how it is,
I know I'm speaking to
a worldwide audience,
so I'm going to speak from
a Netherlands perspective.
and the majority of the
population here is white.
And often, industry at international
products to do with web apps and stuff,
I remember back then there was a huge thing
because it was a group of
young guys in Silicon Valley
who made an app for women
and they had it all wrong.
Why? Because they didn't
have a woman in the team.
So you'd have to do it on day one
and you're gonna hire people
and freelancers and try not,
I know often you listen, you hear a lot is,
“Yeah, but they don't
fit in the work culture.”
See that's the problem,
the work culture.
You want people that
don't fit in your work culture
because your audience and your clients are
not going to be part of your work culture.
So look for people who are
very different from you.
I'm not telling just pick someone
because they're a woman,
because they are brown or
because they are disabled,
you're gonna pick some
because they know the job,
but you're not gonna pick them
because they are the same as you.
So that's the first
thing you have to think.
All righty, that was a fantastic answer.
Could not agree more.
The next one we have up:
YouTube auto captioning is not perfect,
but can those captions be
used as a reference to edit
and fix the errors?
Okay, oh yes.
That's what I do at work too.
We have videos online,
we're captioning them
and yes the advice is you upload on YouTube
and YouTube will generate the auto-caption
and it's going to
be full of mistakes.
And what you can do
is you can edit that file.
So it does help that you
don't have to start from scratch.
So you just get that
auto-generated from YouTube,
that's going to be full of errors
and still will take some work
but at least you're not
starting from scratch.
It will have all the
minutes already noted
and so you just have
to go through that text
and correct all the mistakes
and then you have fine,
well-working captions.
So yes, that's the advice, but never
just generate it and leave it like that.
You can correct them.
Absolutely, that's fantastic.
All right, next question.
Captioning is possible
in YouTube, Vimeo, etc,
but how can I use it in HTML-type videos?
So I guess that means
videos that they've just
embedded directly into the site
and not from a third party?
Well that's a good question.
You have to see the experts on that.
I'm sure today there will be
someone speaking about that.
Because I'm deaf myself, I'm
not able to test these things
and create the captions.
But if I'm not correct—HTML
videos are just embed files,
so you have to like burn the
captions hard-coded in the video.
Because right now YouTube gives you
the options turning it on or off
and Vimeo too,
but if you're gonna embed it in HTML,
then you need to make sure
that you burn those captions in the video.
So that's what I can think about, yes.
Awesome, so this is actually
the last question that I'm seeing, so
but we do have some time
so if anyone has additional questions,
please put them in the chat
so that I can grab them, and
pose them to the speaker here.
So the last question
I'm seeing right now is:
Is it good to use "here"
when providing links
and if not what is the right method?
No, it's not right to use "here".
[Allie laughing]
So always, like,
explain what the link is
and that explanation part going to link,
but here is where? Yes, no.
So if I'm going to link to this
talk later on on my website
I'm going to write, yesterday I gave
a talk to the WordPress Accessibility
You can view my talk on YouTube
and I will link "you can
view my talk on YouTube".
I'm not gonna say you can
view it here, and link here, no.
All right, so we have
one more that just came in.
And the question is:
What are your thoughts on YouTube
community captions being discontinued?
Okay, I think the
YouTube community is very big.
I don't think there is one
YouTube YouTube community,
because inside YouTube
you have several sections.
And I think…
yes, let's say for example since this
pandemic that we have been sitting at home,
I've taken a liking to see these interviews
with writers who release new books.
So they are not going
on book tours anymore,
so everyone is talking to bookstores
on YouTube and several
of them are captioned.
I'm not 100 percent sure if
it's auto caption or not.
I'm going to assume
they were corrected,
because they're pretty good captions,
but there's some I'm missing.
I also like seeing night talk
shows from the United States.
You know, all those
Jimmys—I can't tell them apart,
but I noticed that Conan
never ever has captions.
So I never ever, yes,
Conan and lately I just stumbled
upon him in the recommendation
and I saw he had captions.
But before that Conan
did not have subtitles on YouTube.
And I think it's Kimmel,
Kimmel has subtitles, but his
subtitles are always delayed.
And so it's it's very hit and
miss in the YouTube sphere,
but what I am very upset about
is the decision of Google to
stop community captions.
I don't know if you people have followed,
but Google is gonna stop,
the possibility for people,
like you have a channel
and you have a video
and someone can write the
captions for you and submit it.
But they are going to stop that.
So Google is actively working
against accessibility on that point.
And it was also huge thing with Twitter
because Twitter started voice tweets.
And I want to ask this worldwide audience,
to think twice before you
start using voice tweet,
because they announced voice tweet.
And then everybody was like,
okay what about all the deaf
and hard of hearing people?
And it turns Twitter hadn't even talked
about it with their accessibility team.
It turned out they didn't
really have an accessibility team.
So when people got mad they had
to scramble and get that team set up,
because you cannot take, Twitter is
highly accessible right now, write the text
and you're always giving tips how to
keep the text accessible for screen readers
and now you want to add voice tweets,
that won't be accessible to deaf.
So now the voice tweets are
going to launch soon this year,
and the captions will follow later.
So I'm asking right now to
the worldwide audience
please do not use voice tweets.
Just keep writing your
tweets in so many letters.
There you go.
All right folks, that's all the
questions that I'm seeing for now.
So we are going to go ahead and wrap up.
Thank you Darice so much
for all that fantastic information.
You made so many amazing points
and it was such a pleasure and
an honor to hear you talk today